係。
敷衍，敷衍。
等政府研究。
唔係咁少。
Welcome everyone. Welcome.
其他兩個人都上吊死咗啦。
公眾人士可以即刻參與同埋發表意見。
好誒，政府代表邊一位負責發言咧？
好，唔該曬陳女士。好啊，主席女士啊，係多謝主席。
唔使介紹個application嗰啲喐先，轉頭講之前先講，定還是而家講？
人數都做咗法定時間，我哋馬上開始啦。咁或者我哋呢個時候請有關嘅誒政府代表就進場先。
我哋都啊，同時咧就歡迎我哋嘅今日嘅，welcome，我哋嘅誒公眾人士出席嘅。
女士同埋康啊康樂嘅文化事務處文化事務高級參事，負責研究及發展嘅葉嘉麗先生，歡迎五位。
好，我哋誒基本上我哋客人都基本上坐低咗啦。或者呢個就請我誒或請我哋嘅政府代表就有關嘅文件咧，作個初步嘅簡介先。咁然之後，我會邀請公眾人士再有啲嘅誒公眾嘅發表意見，然之後先輪到委員啦，再誒或者係發表意見，好冇？
好啊，或者由於我哋今次希望可以係一次過咧，將誒有關嘅討論嚇同埋誒聽取誒公眾人士意見做一一齊做啦，所以我哋或者都同時邀請誒有關嘅公眾人士進場，等我哋可以做一個比較係全面性嘅討論。一方面有政府代表，另一方面有。
親呢個時候，或者我為咗工作人士嘅介紹起見咧，就都坐讀今日我哋嘅政府代表啦，包括係有民政事務局嘅首席助理秘書長陳泳詩女士啦，民政事務局嘅助理秘書長樑子康先生同民政事務總署嘅鄭君任先生啦，民政事務總署嘅梁婉瑩。
好多謝主席。
OK，唔好意思，請繼續嚇。
For those who can understand Cantonese, good and well.
嚟做一啲社區活動，咁宗教活動亦都係可以嘅。
咁長租咧，亦都可以係符合條件之下咧，係得到豁免嘅。
You you can just turn on the channels to channel number two and you will find the right channel for your for the English channel, right?
噉就住其他社區會堂同埋社區中心嘅設施咧，就係民政事務總署負責啦。
咁而申請嘅設施咧，亦都可以咧係按個樓層面積咧係以優惠率咧計算地價或者租金嘅。
咁根據現行嘅政策咧，民政事務局咧係可以就宗教團體呢啲申請咧係給予政策嘅支持嘅。
咁喺少數族裔人士去使用公共服務方面咧，如果係需要一啲支援嘅話咧，支援中心咧亦都係樂意去提出協助嘅。
咁民政總署核下有一百零五間社區會堂同社區中心，亦都可以係公開畀所有嘅誒社區團體啦，包括少數族裔團體啦，係去申請。
咁此外咧，民政事務總署咧亦都委託非牟利機構咧營辦六間少數族裔人士支援服務中心，同埋兩間分中心啦，去為少數族裔人士咧提供支援嘅。
咁喺文化活動方面咧，康文署咧為少數族裔咧亦都舉辦同類型嘅文化活動啦，亦都安排咧少數族裔嘅表演者或者團體咧喺佢哋嘅文化節目當中咧係演出嘅。
噉我或者我簡單介紹個文件啦。咁文件介紹咗咧，誒就住民政事務局、民政事務總署同埋康樂文化事務處提供畀少數族裔人士進行宗教同文化活動嘅支援嘅。
誒噉，政府咧已經提交咗一份討論文件啦。噉我呢度做個簡單嘅介紹。好誒，對住請你聽下先啊。誒，for those of you have to rely on interpretation，can you just please put on the earpiece in front of you？
噉就住宗教設施方面咧，民政事務局公民事務部咧係負責同宗教團體聯繫啦。喺本港嘅宗教事務上咧，係擔當協調嘅角色嘅。咁如果喺誒宗教團體咧，可以按佢嘅需要咧，向地政總署申請使用政府土地去發展宗教設施啦。
Funeral parlour for our Muslim community.
人士發言嘅先請嘅咧，就係誒。
就就係盡快請我哋今日嘅公眾人士，第一位同事。
Mr. Youssef Zab Rasheed, please of the Global Social Services Limited.
哦，Thank you. I would like to emphasise on the religious activities first.
Two prayers in different timings, but still we see a lot of troubles because we can't use the
咁喺文件當中咧，我哋都提到誒有一啲嘅例子，噉我喺呢度咧唔再重複啦。咁主席，我嘅簡介係咁多。好。
first of all, I would like to mention that due to the venues limitation, most of our religious activities in the new territories region, such as Yulong,
誒各位同事，大家都知道文件上邊咧，我哋有三份咧，包括係當政府當局嘅文件啦，就係誒四七三stroke十七type十八零一咧，有秘書處嘅一啲資料嘅文件係黑誒fs零一。
誒，數十七、even十八咧，同埋有葉劉淑儀議員嘅一份文件咧，就係喺C B Two三三零slash十七至十八零一嘅。噉就喺呢個階段咧，或者我哋都誒誒安排我哋嘅誒參與誒會議嘅誒公眾人士發言啦。噉就誒提一提大家咧，誒。
剛才都講過關於個耳筒嘅使用啦，大家可以係喺一號個頻道咧係廣東話版本啦，二號頻道有英文版本啦，而三號係普通話嘅版本嘅。咁大家嘅發言時間咧，我哋係三分鐘。誒，亦都誒，大家如果係仲未提供有關書面嘅意見書，係想咁做嘅話，你都喺會後可以補交。
秘書處嘅睇嚟，大家咧就喺今日嘅發言咧。由於大家係不受呢個立法會權及特權條例所保障嘅咧，所以大家應該誒清楚呢一個噉嘅情況咧，而都希望明大家明白到咧係大會都提供咗秘書處提供畀大家一個公眾人士須知嘅情況，需要大家注意注意嘅。好噉，如果我哋誒爭取時間咧，我哋。
Sports, cricket sport as well. Thank you. Thanks very much.
跟住我哋請誒公民黨九龍西地區發展主任張佩琪小姐，唔該，張小姐。
咁加上咧喺新界嘅人口裏邊咧，其實誒少數族裔係增加咗一倍。
哋咧又因為個教育水平咧，其實令佢哋難以去提交一個教有系統嘅計劃書去申請呢個場地舉辦文化活動嘅。
為佢哋提供更多嘅場合，即係可以畀佢哋誒進行公誒宗宗教同埋文化活動，咁幫佢哋咧可以即係維持自身嘅文化同埋宗教嘅特色同傳統嘅。
清真寺為例啦，因為咧有鐵路工程，咁所以嚟緊十二月底咧都會即係誒要交翻呢個地段，咁希望即係政府可以正視呢一個嘅即係問題就可以啦。唔該。
festivals that come every year, which is Eid al-Fitr and Eid al-Azha, so these are very important festivals that hold both in religious activities and cultural activities at the same time, and
From where I have come, has hindered a lot and disturbed most of of the religious activities, such as the special prayer on Friday. Due to our space issues, we can't afford a large number of people to perform the prayer at once. Therefore, we have arranged like two.
space properly and then due to space shortage we have to use the street outside and using the street outside we face a lot of difficulties such as complaints from the local people and this is one of the difficulties that we are kind of facing so also in new territories region we have no
This has been like going on for like decades now. The only funeral parlour we see is in Happy Valley, or sometimes there's some procedures performed in Wan Chai Mosque. So we really recommend one funeral parlour to be implemented in new territories for.
That the community, the Pakistani community, which is the largest, over 50% living in new territories, can perform their funeral activities in new territories. So, if possible, sorry, if possible, then there should be one funeral.
Power in new territories as well, and coming to the cultural activities, same same issue again for the space. Mostly our festivals or wedding parties or other activities often happen in small scale due to space issues or expensive accommodation.
So we are facing similar problems in new territories as well. So we recommend, like if possible, you could like provide us more open space such as parks. If parks can give us the permission to perform our cultural activities, such as our two main.
most of all, I would like to emphasise on sports as well, because cricket has been a sport in our community for a long, long time. Sport is a very famous activity nowadays, not just to our community but also Hong Kong people. So we suggest if there can be a venue for
係咁誒，根據咧啱啱二零一六年中期人口簡要報告指出啦，咁香港嘅人口咧大約有五十八萬非華裔人士，咁佔我哋總人口八個percent。咁因為咧誒，人口越嚟越多，但係咧相應嘅文化同康樂設施其實係冇增加過嘅。
咁誒，我哋咧好少見到即係新界嗰邊有呢個誒，畀少數族裔去進行宗教或者文化儀式嘅場地。噉佢哋咧誒好多時都係喺翻九龍區或者港島區進行嘅。咁所以公民黨咧都建議政府咧可以因應翻相應嘅措施。
往往就需要租住、租借一啲私人屋苑嘅地方啦，或者係申請區內嘅社區會堂去進行呢個宗教活動。
誒一啲畀誒誒消除呢啲一係形式嘅歧視，特別係宗教方面歧視嘅，即係一啲保障噉樣，政府應該做好呢方面之先咯。即係我覺得，政府喺講場地之前，真係唔該諗一諗呢一啲消除宗教歧視嘅即係相關嘅教育噉樣啦，唔該。
但係咧，租用私人地方嘅場地咧有限制啦，面積亦都限制咗參與嘅人數，亦都有時間上面嘅限定。居住喺呢一區嘅印度人士唔止一次向我透露，其實好想喺東湧區由一個固定嘅地方進行佢哋嘅宗教活動，但係亦都唔知道點樣同政府爭取。
咁誒，而家現行嘅做法咧，就係用一啲短期嘅租約咧，去批出土地去作為宗教使用啦。咁其實誒呢個做法並唔理想嘅，因為咧，基於個語言障礙啦，同埋佢哋嘅文化差異咧，其實少數族裔咧偏向係即係同鄉裏來往比較多，噉佢哋。
噉我哋都希望啦，即係而家誒香港咧，其實有六座主要嘅誒清真寺啦，同埋一座嘅石刻廟。咁但係咧新界裏邊咧，其實有超過五成嘅少數族裔咧，都係享用唔到呢個設施嘅。咁一般都要跨區去享用嘅。咁誒，我哋都希望。
啦，即係誒可以即係政府主動少少啦，即係去覓地幫佢哋進行土地規劃嘅時候咧，可以考慮到少數族裔嘅需要，咁將佢哋嘅宗教啦同埋文化咧視為即係一項基本嘅需要啦。咁誒，譬如而家咧油麻地誒，啱啱嗰個易卜拉欣。
唔該，張主席。跟住我哋有請誒社會民主連線嘅陳文威先生，唔該。喂喂喂，係多謝主席。咁首先第一就係其實啱啱提過啦，即係誒有越嚟越多嘅即係穆斯林人口啦。第二就係即係有啲舊嘅數啦。咁因為我唔知道新嘅數字係幾多，但係佢有二十萬，我估有多無少，二十萬嘅穆斯林人口。咁而全。
講其實得六間清真寺，呢個係非常之少嘅數量嚟嘅。第一就係，第二就係咧，即係其實即係當然老實講啦，即係就算叫政府起多啲清真寺，其實我哋都唔expect政府真係會做，因為即係一路以嚟個做嘢效率都咁慢。咁但係即係誒有啲故事就係話曾經喺地區，即係當我仲係一個即係喺葵涌村嘅誒組織幹事嘅時候，即係見到一個。
情況就係有一個地區嘅長老，佢全區即係全個葵涌嘅人口，就喺即係牧師人物細仔喺曬佢嗰度讀《可蘭經》嘅噉。然之後即係佢屋企好細噉啊，想幫佢即係爭取一個即係啊康文署或者係誒扶人嘅設施，去畀佢哋定期有一個嘅活動去到進行呢啲宗教嘅活動噉樣啦。咁但係即係康文署嘅活
回應咧，畀我回應係話：喂，其實佢哋可以自己book嘅喎。咁但係呢個非常虛偽説辭嘅噉樣。咁誒係第二就係好啦。咁申請唔到場地，咁希望透過申請一個更加大嘅即係公屋單位去畀佢進行呢啲噉樣嘅即係誒宗教活動噉樣啦。最尾政府嘅即係回答，即係房署嘅回答就係話：喂，你間屋係啱人口比例㗎啦。
啊，即係冇得搬大啲嘅啦。噉樣噉，其實我覺得個問題係即係簡單嚟講，第一一定係政府係應該畀錢去自己起呢一啲清真寺，起多啲清真寺噉樣。第二個可能就係即係畀錢一啲宗教團體去到起多啲清真寺，但係政府一路都冇做噉樣啦。咁其實我覺得背後個問題反映非常嚴重嘅就係一個叫宗教歧視嘅問題。我覺得係因為唔單單係講。
講緊即係有多誒，即係誒誒誒，我哋見到香港永生永久性居民身份嘅一啲穆斯林噉樣啦。特別係一啲即係外容團體，其實佢哋誒外容特別係外容啦。佢哋面對一個好大宗教歧視，例如即係有一個叫做加尼嘅啊，印尼回教徒嘅組織，佢哋嘅其中一個領袖叫做Rossy咧，佢就同我講翻就係話誒外容。
面對好大嘅宗教歧視。第一，佢哋可能會有啲即係誒文化上嘅需要，佢哋一日要祈禱五次，但係因為工作所需，佢哋嘅誒僱主係唔會畀佢喺一日祈禱五次嘅。第二就係即係佢哋喺齋戒月嘅時候可能要禁食禁水，有有好多外傭試過佢哋唔食嘢，畀畀僱主打噉樣。第二就係啲。
家細負負累事。
on colon side， we only have one mosque。
一萬六百萬個穆斯林living in Hong Kong。
是full support and cooperation to the Muslim community.
我係副主席兼總幹事，香港伊斯蘭社區基金會。
We also need attention from the government department to have a more friendly policy towards the EM.
We are managing all the five mosque and two Muslim cemetery given by the government of Hong Kong.
在過去10年，我們觀察到政府，特別是HAB，給予EM更多關注，但這並不足夠。
我們現今邀請總幹事暨香港伊斯蘭社區基金會的董事長賽義德·厄頓。
我 wish to convey my thanks to the LEGCO for giving me the opportunity to attend the subcommittee meeting of the Rights of E.M. on discuss the provisions of venues in districts to for ethnic minorities conduct religious and cultural activities.
which is not sufficient to serve the large Muslim population living in different parts of Kowloon. About more than 300,000 Muslims live in Hong Kong, including 150,000 Indonesian Muslim sisters who also attend prayers on Friday and Sunday.
到而家咧，仍然都未有更加詳細嘅計劃。噉我希望政府喺平衡各方嘅利益之下啦，可以多啲接觸區裏邊印度籍嘅人士，可以聽下佢哋嘅訴求。誒，亦都協助佢哋喺區內宗教活動嘅發展。多謝主席。
僱主特別係老人家會逼佢哋食豬肉噉樣，即係如果佢哋唔食就打佢噉樣。誒第三種情況就係話誒有好多外傭團體喺維園，又或者係唔同嘅即係政府嘅公共設施嗰度去進行呢啲活動，要用音響，試過畀一啲保安趕走佢哋，話佢哋唔可以喺度進行活動。第四種情況就係咧，佢哋有啲誒宗教活動嘅需要。
係攬一啲白色頭巾，有啲黑色頭巾噉樣。咁但係僱主就特係誒，即係特別係唔畀佢哋攬呢頭巾噉樣，即係佢哋其實受到一個好大嘅宗教歧視。其實政府喺講話畀多啲活動場地佢哋之前咧，即係唔該諗一諗，你諗一諗呢個問題。即係其實世界人權宣言講到好清楚，我哋嘅教育上面係應該做好。
好唔該，陳生，跟住嚟，有請新聞黨嘅傅曉林女士。唔該，多謝主席。咁根據二零一六年嘅人口普查裏邊啦，咁香港咧就總共大約有五十八萬四千名少數族裔嘅人口啦。咁而家咧，香港其實有好多個宗教並存，而較多少數族裔人士嘅宗教咧，分別係伊斯蘭。
教同埋印度教，咁大約分別有三十萬教徒啦，同埋十萬嘅教徒。咁而東湧區咧喺二零一六年中期人口嘅統計裏邊咧，按種族劃分嘅人口比例，除咗華人之外咧，第二多嘅人就係印度人啦。可見區內聚居嘅少數人族裔咧，其實位數係唔少啦。
更加需要正視佢哋日常生活嘅需要，好似東湧北為例，咁有好多少數族裔居住，例如印度人啦。咁大約有數百個家庭，噉佢哋以前咧就一直都冇一個固定嘅場所進行呢個宗教嘅文化活動。咁對於佢哋嚟講咧，宗教文化活動其實係生活嘅一部分，但係佢哋咧往
而全香港咧，其實只有幾座清真寺啦，全部亦都係集中喺市區。咁顯然係唔足以容納咁多嘅小數族裔嘅教徒啦，亦都要佢哋另覓場所去進行呢一個宗教嘅儀式，令佢哋每次咧做宗教儀式嘅時候就好似小番檔噉樣招行用招行晚茶嘅形式去進行，亦。
都好阻礙佢哋宗教嘅發展。噉佢哋話，雖然可以喺市區嘅清清真寺進行崇拜啦，咁但係路途又好遠，車資對佢哋嚟講咧，亦都會構成呢個負擔，亦都好難恆常咁參與呢個宗教活動。咁長遠而言咧，佢哋好希望喺東湧咧，亦都有一座清真寺啦，畀佢哋。
進行宗教儀式之外咧，亦都有在營助少數族裔嘅居民，更加融入市社區嘅生活。咁政府去年底亦都曾經諮詢過離島區議會啦。咁有意將東出北公園旁邊嘅用地畫作政府機構或者社區設施嘅用途，留作日後宗教發展之用啦。不過到
Board of Trustees is extremely grateful to the Government for the Hong Kong Special Administrative Region and all its departments for providing an atmosphere of freedom of speech and expression in Hong Kong to members of EM who belongs to different religious and ethnicity. The Muslim community of Hong Kong in particular is thankful to the Government for extending
As you know, the Muslim community in Hong Kong is expanding at a fast rate, due to which the Muslim, the masjid we are available presently are insufficient to cater the religious needs of Muslim community. Out of five mosques, four are in Hong Kong and in Hong Kong land, and only one mosque is in Kowloon side.
喺昌沙橋，was built in one thousand, nine hundred and eighty four. Due to scarcity of places of worship, members of Muslim community finds extremely difficult to offer their prayers. They cannot even come from the new territories or anywhere else. The majority of Muslim community living in Hong in Kowloon side have homes in.
係。
多謝主席。
Large Eid.
供納唔到我哋而家現有嘅需求。
我哋係幫啲青誒青少年誒去去誒畀啲服務佢哋啦。
咁亦都有好多啲遊客都會會會嚟誒誒，我哋嗰度去誒perform佢哋嗰個禮拜啦。
噉我哋亦都二零零七年咧做誒誒註冊咗誒慈善機構誒undersection八十八嘅。
Hong Kong to provide free of cost venues for conducting religious and cultural activities. Thank you very much. Thank you very much, Mr. We now invite Mr. Elias Mohammed, please.
噉我哋亦都誒誒成功誒二零一三年咧申誒申請一個短期租約，咁誒喺喺油麻地嘅，咁誒亦都係批咗畀我哋啦。噉我哋一直都係用緊呢個地方啦，叫Mustapha Ibrahim。
咁逢星期日啦假期咧，噉我哋亦都有好多啲飛鴻都會過嚟，噉啊誒都會去去去用呢個設施嘅。噉我哋我哋計個條數咧，平均一誒一日咧，我哋有差唔多五百個人去去用用緊呢一個centre，去去去去做佢哋個禮拜啦，同埋其他啲activities。
大馬泰、柬埔寨、中沙灣、東灣、廣東和香港等，他們安排一些地方的崇拜在私人建築物上租用，這是非常昂貴的管理。因此，我們迫切需要新的永久崇拜的地方，以減少財務。
負擔於社區，它被要求提供新的祭拜場地在免費的基礎上。除了提供祭拜場地外，它還被要求在每個區提供合適的場地，在臨時基礎上舉辦我們的文化活動，例如齋月、開齋月和穆斯林。
依都fit啊，依都得。On behalf of the board of trustee and DAB ethnic committee, which I am member also looking for the the ethnic minority affairs, the Islamic Committee of Hong Kong Muslim, I request members of the subcommittee to rights of the ethnic minority to make a strong recommendation to government of
咁誒誒，首先我誒介紹下啦。噉我哋係誒誒United Welfare Union Hong Kong Limited誒誒去誒代表誒今日去講話嘅。噉我哋係二零零二年咧就係誒承辦咗呢個United Welfare Union啦。咁誒誒投入服務，咁誒最主要就係。
噉我哋現有咧有三三度誒centre，咁誒東湧啦、油麻地啦，同埋呢個淘嘉環嘅。噉我哋誒，因為香全香港得五間誒清真寺啫。咁誒誒誒，頭先阿司都丁都講咗啦。咁有四個就喺香港度嘅，一個咧就喺喺尖沙咀九龍嘅。咁誒根本就係誒用。
噉我哋誒一般逢星期五咧啲人太多，噉我哋包括呢個油麻地啦、佐敦啦、旺角啊，同埋其他區都會有好多人會過嚟去做做嗰個禮拜嘅。咁但係因為太多人容納唔到，噉我哋都要分開兩個session去去去去進行呢個誒誒禮拜啦。
嗯。
幾多？
誒。
一年嘅。
誒，拖牛節啦，同埋呢個齋戒月。
噉我哋我哋我哋誒誒誒。
咁呢啲所有服務都係係係免費嘅。
perhaps then may we have Mr. Per Khan please.
誒嗰個誒租租金咧係太貴啦，三十九萬幾。
變咗我哋係根本就係係係afford唔到去去去去去。
咁誒呢個齋計月咧，我哋亦都會會會會去安排啲食物啊，去去去開齋啊，噉啊朝頭早時間亦都會有呢啲噉嘅arrangement喺度嘅。
噉我哋亦都有誒超過一百個誒小朋友咧，我哋係教緊佢哋可能經啦。咁亦都有長者都會每一日差唔多有五十個都會係到到我哋嗰個centre去去做佢哋個禮拜或者成嘅。
also below the same group, okay, and the back also, good, thanks very much. What about Mr Zubair Muhammad? Also, all right, okay. How about Mr Vero Sumitha, the Sri Lankan Buddhist Cultural Centre? Yes, please, thank you.
誒去交呢個噉嘅費用啦，咁希望你哋可以幫幫手睇下，可可唔可以同政府傾下，睇下可以盡量係減低嗰個誒月租畀我哋咯。好，多謝。Mr. Mohamed，誒，we will now invite Mr. Khan Asif please。So already. You want to say something on your own, or you want? Okay, fine, right.
啊！
呃，until。
actually。
because there is a specific way。
The end of 2016.
在斯里蘭卡傳統、佛教傳統。
They have missed that chance as well.
for them to perform their religious activities.
最後， homage for their death relatives.
他們沒有，甚至一處，甚至一平方米。
Sometimes they need to do.
呃，for performing斯里蘭卡宗教和 cultural events.
斯里蘭卡佛教文化中心在香港，是個新開的機構。
when they are they have leisure time, they need to spend their time in a park or in a separated place alone.
斯里蘭卡人社區 did not have their own place to perform their cultural and religious activities.
on behalf of Sri Lankan community in Hong Kong, I would like to present this request for your consideration.
包我哋啲服務包括咧，噉我哋一個月咧平均計個條數係一萬五千個穆斯林係會到我哋嗰個清真寺去去做個禮拜啦。咁誒，我哋個時間咧係朝頭早五點至到夜晚九點鐘嘅。噉我哋亦都一年會舉辦兩次嘅大嘅活動，就係我哋個誒誒呢個。
嗯。
誒。
誒，誒。
end of.
誒，所以誒。
We don't have a permanent place.
and we have started.
所以，The thing is that.
實踐，作為斯里蘭卡文化活動。
2016，所以 now almost one year，所以 we are practicing both Theravada Buddhist。
to pay last homage for their death relatives, so they missed that chance as well. So I came to Hong Kong in order to my higher education.
When I see these people, according to my understanding, there are more than two thousand Sri Lankans are living in Hong Kong. Most of them are domestic helpers.
After I came to understand that these people do not have a separated place, I dedicated my time to start a new place. So we received a place under the rental basis.
我哋係冇任何收費嘅。咁呢度呢度，我哋全部都係用用我哋嘅誒donation去去去去去運作緊嘅。咁近排咧，我哋喺東湧咧都啱啱早幾日先收到誒話批咗個短期租約出嚟畀我哋嘅。咁呢個短期租約，我哋都申請咗好幾年㗎啦。咁但係個問題就係因為佢哋。
school， I mean the where Buddhism and Sri Lankan culture and Sri Lankan mother language is taught. That school for kids. Now we have nearly one hundred Sri Lankan kids studying there.
In case sometimes we don't know, since that is not our own place, we need to leave when the landlord ask us to leave. So I would like to request you, if there is any possibility for you, to provide us a small piece of land.
在香港，我們可以發展我們斯里蘭卡佛教文化中心，為斯里蘭卡社區以及香港其他人士的福祉。謝謝。非常感謝。我們現在請James Guran，來自香港的日本基督教會有限公司。
嗯。
點知？
Our problem.
We have the big problem.
另一個是 Easter。
excuse me， thank you for invitation。
Same way， we have the problem in the churches， very small places。
啊，our festival is the big festival. One is the Christmas.
and then our system we do the our combine youth.
and bring their activities and their cultural, their everything's and their relig religious activities, but we
我係 come from the Methodist Christian Council in Hong Kong， and I am the now the the president of the Methodist Council。
1830s， they are serving the on， on import， lending the， property。
conference，every year one times， and at least minimum one time is the whole church's family conference in one times in in the year。
In since one thousand nine hundred and ninety four, in here and when establish the Nepalese residentially living in the here now, since one thousand nine hundred and ninety four now two thousand seventeen, we are here Nepalese language on language sources.
是18個教會，喺香港，most of churches in the Jordan Yamatai，喺the Mong Kok， and one of one of the Wan Chai， and second largest number of people， Nepalese people living in the Yuen Long in the New Territories， and as like the Kam Tin in the Yuen Long and
啊，program。
會people，有啲many many people。
openly without any hesitation. Thank you. Thank you very much.
We now have Mr. Saba Sabita of the Bethel Mission Church Limited, please.
permanent place and yearly three time or four time we can do our.
但係， so many threatening we bearing the there because and the neighbour is complaining.
to do the to do especially in our festival or any other um
like a festival, like a wedding and birthday and and in our any program, so we are seeking the government consideration.
但係，我們 facing many difficulties 因為 not enough space。 we we we can do a lot of we can do
this four four times we have to need in the big hall, but still now we have no any hall and we request and we application many times we could not as well to we approve by from the legislative council or district council, so also in the
we every Sunday we worship in the worship and we use the music and the song in the worship and then in the disturbing the our neighbour and then complain sometime police coming many many things are happenings. still 18 churches in the neighbourhood churches, here no any place in the government place by supporting.
政府， and no any supporting the donation from the government and any other charity. We are doing the on our ourselves with our effort. First of all, I like to inform Hong Kong government, if possible, please provide for us as one.
yes sir I'm Sumba Sabita, Secretary of Bethel Mission Church in Hong Kong. So I'm speaking on behalf of Nepalese Church. Our church started since two thousand and fourteen with few ethnic minority family. We are renting a room of seven hundred square feet.
meter， but it is very expensive. Now we are seventy to eighty person caring the caring twenty to twenty five family. We are doing religious and cultural program every Sunday and every Wednesday and every morning.
for the devotional prayer, and also we are providing accommodation for Nepalese and Indian foreign domestic helper on their off day, as well as cultural and spiritual support to them, and also we we are doing.
Christmas program, Easter program, youth youth program and woman fellowships, and we do children program also. And also we we are doing the family counseling and spiritual and religious as well as parenting counseling for the ethnic minorities families and person.
係。
District.
Thank you.
其居民，然而，似乎即使最 fundamental 個別需求亦未得到滿足。
非常感謝，Mr Wong。 now， we have Mr Shakhi Ali Saka Mohamed， please。
Thank you, Mr. Speaker。誒，跟住我哋有請扶輪大嶼山社會服務團顧問黃祖興先生嘅，唔該，黃生。
第三點是，有長久被頻繁注意到，有許多中國人，以及非中國人年輕人，巴基斯坦、印度、尼泊爾，無目的在東城區遊蕩。他們顯然需要一些建設性活動，否則他們會被推到犯罪邊緣。
或提供更多活動 for the long term，因為缺乏資源，這些是 organisation，或我們做自己的支援，and we must need the place or venue of to
Good afternoon, Chairman, respectful, respectful councillors, government officials and geo colleagues. I'm Andrew Wong from the Community Service Corps of the Rotary Club of Lantau. A while ago, Mr. General, the Civil Party had revealed the number of non-Chinese population in Hong Kong, but the fact has not been revealed that the non-Chinese population have been gradually
increase over the years in Lantau, especially in Dong Jung area. Take for example Indians, there are presently over one thousand families living in Lantau Island, and foreseeable the numbers to be escalated in the coming years. For the development of North Lantau, the government's long term policy towards forward is aimed at providing opportunities and quality living to.
We, for instance, the civil engineering and development department and and the now chief executive, had been met and asked to take into account the needs of non-Chinese, aside Chinese, when striving to achieve its targets. However, the requesting parties have never received anything on the progress so far.
Our points are crystal clear. The Chinese and non-Chinese are currently facing the same difficulty to maintain their religious pattern while living in Lantau. There are few churches, mosques, which have capacity adequate enough to hold Christians and Muslims, and none for the Indian residents to enshrine the gods for worship.
The current picture is that the latter is that they are celebrating their festivals and gathering in Dongcheng regularly in clubhouses or private housing estates, of which the capacity are apparently not not not enough. Besides, many religious rituals have not been allowed due to restrictions in closed clubhouse settings. Sufficient places.
應該被提供給建造大型教堂、清真寺的Lantau。第二個點是，隨著數量非中國家庭移居Lantau，是合理的讓孩子被接受到同一地區的學校。然而，由於當地學校提供免費教育，還未改善英語標準，大多數非中國學生有困難。
要調整自己以適應環境。社區因此期待有個較便宜及政府經營的學校，供非中國學生由學術資格教師，任何國籍，而具足夠的英語溝通能力。具體計劃應制定於新學校的建設，供非中國學生，即新移民。
MJC XRL。
我 mention to them.
但已經 done 呢？這 area。
require this land, but we found that I mentioned if you want, I can read it to this. What I write to them.
We are working with a home office bureau for the policy support at alternative land source.
二零一八，和這塊地是應該被交給西雅圖馬泰西科納特州。
One day of the contractor' commitment is that portion of the land is where the contractor and engineer office is located.
hence we give a bit more time for us to work with the Home Affairs Bureau to find an alternative plan and to avoid our community.
The our prayer hall already started. Its construction site is MTR, MTRC XRL project is since we got the land in February two thousand thirteen.
Contractor adjacent to our prayer hall land is currently doing the road works until work has Hoi Yan Road in front of our prayer hall and hand.
hence the secure construction site surrounding our prayer hall, all will will be will not have any difference to our prayer hall, all use since we started using it is two thousand thirteen.
and had mentioned that their overall completion date as 26 June 2018, and the Yamatai West Contracted Our Prayer Hall land portion cannot be commenced at the earliest by July 2018.
eviction from the current land without any alternative prayer hall, and anyhow we, as our prayer hall land will be lying unused at least until July 2000, July to December 2018.
The construction of more appropriate leisure places, including cricket pitch, sports centres, activity rooms, community halls, safe grounds for riding bikes and scooters, should be reserved for them, so as to allow them to play their familiar games and engagement in their cultural activities, especially celebration in the festival days. Thank you.
Good evening. We are the same, so even I can say I can say also some word for this. Sure, by all means, please also. I send the letter for Mujibrahim in Yamate to Land Department, which is the expiry date on thirty first December this month.
We are very worried for that, and I write a letter to. We work on that project, secure project, and I found there this land still is secure, is no required for them, but they insist this land to return, and we we are looking for the government to alternative if they really.
2018 until 2018, 18 months will not require this land. Even in in secure project, they don't have this piece of land in in their the workplace. Their and they mentioned is that the the heavy work is running in that place that area.
MTRC XRL Construction can occupy the site adjacent to our prayer hall, which also comes under the same Yamate Waste Contract HI Stroke 2014 Stroke 20. As our prayer hall land will be occupying the land at least until April.
係。
多謝。
food cuisine classes and so on.
Between Chinese and Turkish community.
and try to introduce the cultures of the two community to the other one.
在香港，因為來自於相同的伊斯蘭背景。
Our long-time experience and observation is that both communities.
until it is really needed to be given to the contractor.
although Turkish community is not that populated in Hong Kong, we have many common things with major Muslim ethnic minority groups.
尊敬的成員們，作為安納託利亞文化與對話中心，一間註冊慈善機構，我們正努力形成橋樑。
We now invite Mr. Ibrahim Erdem Kanga of the Anatolia Cultural and Dialogue Centre Limited, PR manager. Thanks.
since our establishment, 2007, we have organised many academic and non-academic talks, seminars, interfaith activities, iftar dinners for non-Muslims, courses, art programmes, festivals and
to build it, we sincerely request the government to please extend our lease at least until December 2018. And also, as the construction period of this project is around six years, at the completion.
Date of the landscape due in our Perahoe land portion 11 is around five years from the handover date of April 2019. As portion 11, I have to stop you there somewhere. Sorry about that, but we can give you some more time later on, please. Thank you very much, Mohamed.
Let this land be useful to our community. We fully understand that our prayer hall land is to be handed over to the highway department for CKR project. Yamatai West Colon contractor and we would be fully aware that. But what we are asking is to let our community use the current land.
But.
In our opinion.
Chinese and the other.
to work on this issue.
在穆斯林社會。
但係，仲有空間發展。
There might be laws and government and non-government bodies effort.
and it will help local people to accept ethnic minority to their society in real sense.
Their culture and daily living is dominantly shaped with Islam, naturally, as well as local customs.
The institutions focusing on ethnic minority integration are in need of venue and premise for their programmes, like us.
There might be some places government is offering, but demand and supply somehow cannot meet, or it is not enough for the need of ethnic minorities.
更多 programmes， like talks, seminars and interactive programmes are needed to be organised by ethnic minority groups and government organisations.
所以，要 inform 個體社會人士有關宗教和文化知識，是必要的，以促進社會關係。
communities, the other ethnic minority communities, do not know much about the other culture and religion, or the information they have is very basic, or have some misinformation.
For example, we have closed our office due to financial problems and continue our programmes on online with random places, which is a great obstacle for us.
On the other hand, to lessen the understanding of the ethnic minority cultures and beliefs for local Chinese people, more programmes and cooperation need need to be performed through those ethnic minority centres.
taking taking into account the handover date of our prayer hall land to the contractor in April two thousand nineteen, and to be utilise the given prayer hall land so as to maximise the return for the huge amount three million dollar spent by our improvement community.
在terms of religion.
和 art and cuisine.
We have something called madrasas in Hong Kong.
教育， in terms of religion and as well as school related.
We cater to Muslim students by providing accommodation, along with education.
especially Turkish community and overall generally Muslim students.
在我們伊斯蘭中心，which are also home to those students，這些係基本係租賃 flats，where students can stay。
to attract public's attention and understanding, more talks and programmes on community level could be designed on ethnic minority culture.
要增加 leisure and culture services departments existing cooperation with ethnic minorities to a higher level is necessary. In conclusion.
香港伊斯蘭文化及 welfare Society 是個註冊社會喺香港，自2009。我們嘅影響範圍係關乎服務穆斯林社區。
I think everybody here is familiar with the term. We provide religious education regarding the Quran, regarding Arabic language, regarding the nature and the history of Islam.
alongside that, we want our students to balance their education, so we provide them with school-related education as well. We have daily tuition classes for different subjects.
我會like to apologise first of all. Our manager wanted to be here but he could not. He had urgent matters regarding to seeking donations, which I will explain soon.
Thank you. Thank you very much, Mr. Conca. We now have Mr. Adnan Muhammad of the Hong Kong Islamic Cultural and Welfare Society, please. Thank you, Chairperson.
Programs targeted to attract people from both communities to let them mix and learn. Otherwise, programmes for ethnic minorities or Chinese are not effective enough.
We need ethnic minority groups need more support on venues and premises, and more cooperation with the leisure and culture and services department.
嗯。
It requires a lot of time and effort, is what I'm saying.
As you understand, language is an important barrier.
當他們去其他，let's say，gatherings for festivals， which are similar。
They are still not openly welcome as such. They cannot communicate properly.
目前， we have two such Islamic centres. One is in Shawkevan， and another one is in Austin.
and easily go to the school. Usually, we try to pick locations close to the school for the school year.
我哋會 now invite Ms. Louisa Tan Castro, Honorary Treasurer of the United Muslim Association of Hong Kong, please.
Hong Kong government does not have any specially special specialised language support for for the Turkish community, nor is there any special educational aid for the children.
在我們社會，我們有週ly gatherings，我們 invite  people from all backgrounds， but especially the Turkish and especially our students.
maintaining this Islamic centre is actually a very costly operation on an annual basis and we have to renew, we have to construct, we have to provide the accommodation, the food, which is actually a very, very expensive and very
It can connect or it can be a barrier. So Chinese people prefer to speak Chinese language. Mostly, I would prefer Urdu or Indians would prefer Hindi and so on. Turkish people therefore would therefore would prefer to speak Turkish.
alongside that, we want to serve the Turkish community, which is mostly isolated from other communities in Hong Kong, both Chinese and other ethnic minorities. Even though Turks are mostly Muslim in Hong Kong, the level of openness between different cultures can be varying.
Our organisation is striving to meet all these needs, along with the overarching aim of providing religious and worldly education for all Muslim youths, not especially the Turkish community. It is very challenging, but we are willing to put in the effort. We would appreciate the support from the government and from our community.
regards the government, if it's possible that such accommodation, such buildings or such locations can be provided to us, either free of charge or subsidised, we would very well welcome that effort, and we are very thankful that we had this opportunity to talk to you. Thank you very much. Thank you very much, Mr Mohamed.
Okay, greetings of peace. Thank you very much for allowing us to attend this meeting. The United Muslim Association of Hong Kong was established in 1997 as a charity and operates a primary school, Yunlong, a home for the elderly, and now we are trying to construct the Islamic centre in Shengshui with an elderly.
and together with the social welfare department.
Technology and subsidised elderly home. Why are we allowed not allowed to establish a school when other international schools are allowed to do so?
Moreover, in order to efficiently supervise the Sham Shui Po Masjid project, another memorandum of understanding was signed with the BOT, the Islamic Community Fund Trustees of Hong Kong.
An MOA, a memorandum of agreement, was signed with the Ministry of Finance of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in 2009, where the late King Abdullah pledged to finance the construction project.
與已故創始人奧馬·哈吉阿里丁，及克服來自當地居民委員會的反對後，透過卡塔爾基金會的慷慨撥款，土地補償已支付。
機會代表東湧印度社區在表達我們的聲請舉辦場地。我會利用這個機會分享我們過去遇到的困難，以及現在正在面臨的挑戰，即在尋找舉辦我們的祭典、活動和文化課程的場地。
project pending our funding of the masjid part. Now I would like to raise the following points. First of all, with regards to the lot, why are we required to ensure building an elderly home when other religious groups in the north district have monasteries and churches which were granted land without such a requirement?
Home project. To give a brief background, a plot of land about 2,046 square metres was acquired in Shengshui in 2006, with a lease premium of 9.35 million, to construct an Islamic centre and a 200-bed elderly care home. This was after more than a decade-long.
要 entrust the project pending the outcome of the litigation by an authorised party claiming leadership of the organisation. Since then, the BOT has contributed to keeping the project alive by lending more than one million Hong Kong dollars to pay land premium penalty to the Lands Department to maintain the lease of this precious land.
我們被給予五年來建造，而那是在2011年。在2016年7月，沙特領事館在香港發送了一封信給香港特別行政區政府，表示他們希望延遲這個項目一段時間。這是在兩次招標活動之後。在之前的幾年，建設部門已經批准了設計。
However, the Lands Department is not prepared to further extend the land lease without concrete evidence of pursuing actual construction. In light of the situation, the Hong Kong government may re-enter this land lot. We have approached various institutions, including the Jockey Club Trust Fund, which may be interested to fund the elderly home.
和precisely the fact that the North District is supposed to have a zoning requirement for religious spaces. Furthermore, why are we required to build from our own meagre resources? According to the Chief Executive Policy Address, the Hong Kong SAR Government plans to set up a 1 billion fund to promote Jeroen.
支持和motivation。
We have already applied.
and thank you，धन्यवाद नंद्री。
Thank you, Dr. Sivakumar. Can we now invite Mr. Imam Mohammed Enis of the Dawati Islami Hong Kong, Chairman of the Association, please?
東區啊，和argent areas，南塔庫、沙旺平、蘭廷、科倫貝、凱塔。In this area, no even South Asian community centre.
with limitations. While our community groups actively perform dances and songs in various cultural events organised by various authorities and associations, these practice sessions also take place once again in the above-stated venues.
We are running ten branches in the Hong Kong different areas, in which seven hundred children learning after school religious and culture classes in our centres.
And why are we not allowed to try to assist the Hong Kong government to review comprehensively the entry requirement of Chinese proficiency and help the EM assist and integrate into society and cultivate positive values through disciplined forces training programme targeting EM youth? Why are we allowed? Why do we have to pay?
such a high premium when other faith groups were not required to do so, and I have emailed the references regarding this. So may we request the subcommittee to review our our case and convey our request to the Hong Kong government to provide assistance to allow us to finally construct this place of worship.
and provide services to our youth and the elderly so that we can serve our own Hong Kong community. Thank you. Thank you very much, Mrs. Castro. Next, we have Dr. Chitra Surpakuma, please. Thank you. Respected members of Lekhika, Namaste, Vannakam. To begin with, I would like to convey my thanks to the Lekhika for giving me this opportunity.
We are now more than thousand households living in the Lantau region. Every year, we organise festivals, yearly events, guest lectures, sports activities and competitions in LCSD Community Hall and various clubhouse function rooms. As Indian festivals involve worshiping of our gods and distribution of food, clubhouses are the only venues available.
Furthermore, we have many regular culture classes teaching not only kids but also adults. Classical dance, music, yoga, cultural values, Indian languages in this area, catering to more than three hundred to four hundred residents. Kindly note that most of these classes are conducted on non-profit basis. All classes and events are now conducted in existing venues.
sadly, those who organise such events, classes and practice sessions face a lot of problems in getting the venue, as there are not enough venues to meet the requirements of all communities living in Tung Chung. I represent all the members of the Indian community in Tung Chung, and in particular the group of people who have contacted government officials in getting a place to conduct religious and
cultural activities for Hindus, specifically for Hindus, for more than seven years. As rightly pointed by Mr. Andrew of Rotary Lantau Community Service Corps, if we can get a school potentially managed by Indians catering to the needs of Tung Chung community, all these problems can be solved, and we can organise our cultural activities, classes and sports activities.
在學校廁所，沒有任何不便。我們印度父母在香港工作，為了讓孩子們在這裡生活得更舒適，我們的孩子，大多數是第三文化孩子，會在多種民族、宗教和文化中迷失，如果不是因為文化課程幫助他們記住自己的身份，知道該走的正確道路。
their lives and safeguard them from the invasion of bad elements in their lives, and become responsible citizens and contribute to the Hong Kong community. Graduating in 2017 with a PhD thesis on intercultural transformation caused by stress and adaptation, I feel that migrants can be shaped to contribute to Hong Kong development with proper.
如果個community，
誒，跟住我哋誒。
Thank you very much. Is that it? Yeah, thank you.
We should keep the community together in every respect.
誒，Escasro所講，即係呢個穆斯林聯會。
政府代表有冇現階段有冇需要發言啊？陳女士，你還是等埋聽埋委員發言之後，你先一時。
now our community is constantly increasing, but we are facing difficulties due to lack of proper venue, place and facilities.
所以，它也是重要考慮，所有社會福利、文化和一般社區工作活動包括在宗教的名義下。
基本嘅活動上面咧，係幾咁缺乏場地啦，幾咁缺乏資源啦。其中有誒兩個項目，我係比較關注嘅，一個就係頭先誒。
如果委員會做好決定，和相關部門提供我們舉辦社區活動的場地，它不僅會促進社區工作，還可以控制社區內的犯罪。
With government support, definitely non-Chinese minorities can adapt the host culture while still not giving away their home culture. Once again, thank you for giving us this opportunity and listening to our plea. We look forward to getting a community centre or a school premises for Indians in Tung Chung, and this will be used by all communities of South Asians.
Thank you, honourable chairman and members and government officers. After listening, we face same problem with us. To Kawan area now industry development area, therefore we face same some venues problems. Especially I mention districts of Colon City and
One of vacant place, but government office bureau is solving ethnic minority's problem difficulties very slow processing and with lengthy communications. Number two, our organisation already apply one place for our South Asian community promotion of our religious culture welfare activities at Natako.
area， but still in pending since five years. While we are completed all requirements in this way, how can we work better for community? As per present situation of high price living life in Hong Kong, we are suggest subcommittee to consider that Hong Kong Housing Authority allocate and offer one premises at their every.
新項目， for ethnic minorities youth and child centre. It is easy to promote ethnic minorities work as per their welfare waiting policy rates. Beside, we we do not know why Hong Kong Housing Department could not release such these places venues while they are available places venue for this task.
在一些政府辦公室、地方，我 suggest 有啲問題喺呢個點。在一些政府辦公室、地方，宗教詞彙被限制，為 allocate 這個場地畀 HSB（香港房屋局）和地政署。
主席可以聽埋委員發言。好，噉我哋而家暫時報咗名有四位同事嘅，或者我哋首先請啊張超雄啊，唔係啊張超雄議員先啦，唔計五分鐘，唔計。好啊，多謝主席，亦都多謝咁多位團體嚟到誒，即係表達少少雋鋭喺宗教啦、文化啦或者其他嘅。
即喺九七年嘅時候咧，提出喺上，即係希望興建一個清真寺啦，同埋呢個伊斯蘭中心啦，仲甚至有安老院啊，啊或者係誒診所啊、小學噉樣。咁呢一個計劃咧，我理解喺九七年嘅時候咧，政府已經揾到上水個幅地。
陳女士。
多謝主席。
政府係有責任去同呢啲居民咧係解釋。
活動嘅用地嘅一點啦，以及係個別嘅個案嘅。
考慮給予政策支持，咁好似喺討論文件所講啦。誒，我哋亦都會考慮咧，係以一個優惠率咧去計算一個地價同埋誒租金嘅。
亦都會考慮畀政策支持，咁亦都咧跟住咧就會同規劃處咧去聯係，噉就邀請規劃處咧跟佢申請者嘅要求咧去物識合適嘅政府土地去興建呢一啲嘅宗教設施嘅。
申請咁其實係有兩大嘅方向嘅。第一大咧就係誒覓地嘅申請。如果宗教團體咧係未有一啲誒特定嘅選址嘅話咧，係可以咧向民政事務局咧係提交一個誒詳細嘅計劃書啦。
點係點？噉我想政府咧正面回應翻頭先，即係我除咗我講呢兩個例子之外咧，頭先咁多團體講關於佢哋個誒祈禱啦、進行一啲宗教儀式咧，或者一啲誒文化嘅活動咧，缺乏場地嘅問題。好啊。
噉啊，好可惜，即係搞咁耐咧，仍然係未落實得到。咁呢個誒，其實係今日平機會個誒文件都有顯示咧。誒有啲學者都指示咧，呢個係香港對於少數族裔或者對於宗教歧視嘅一個例子嚟嘅。
咁呢樣係事實上讓香港蒙羞，其中即係當然我哋見到有啲當區嘅居民咧，可能係唔認識呢個誒穆斯林教或者回教，或者佢哋對呢個誒少數族裔嘅生活亦都唔認識。我覺得政
作出一啲詳細嘅諮詢，嚟到克服呢啲困難。而就算個補地價咧，亦都係嚟曬普，即係我哋見到鄉議局成幅地佢嘅總部興建咧，補地價我理解係得一千蚊嘅啫。佢哋咧就要畀一千萬，咁呢個係咪一個明顯嘅歧視咧？
另外，灣仔嗰個嘅對唔住呢個誒油麻地區嗰個嘅葉卜拉恩清真寺咧，而家面對因為要誒嗰個沙中線嗰個工程咧影響咧，佢要交翻成個地段，我又亦都好擔心呢一個清真寺咧未來嗰個發展。
誒或者我喺回應個別嘅個案之前，我一並回應頭先團體提到嘅幾點啦，包括係想會有一啲永久嘅用地係外嚟做一啲宗教同文化活動嘅一點啦，以及係進行一啲誒康樂或者體育文化。
噉就住宗教用地方面咧，根據現行嘅政策咧，民政事務局咧係可以咧就住宗教團體申請政府土地去興建一啲宗教設施咧，係給予政策支持嘅。咁喺呢個宗教團體提出申請嘅過程當中咧，民政事務局咧亦都會協助處理。
咁當中列明有關嘅宗教設施嘅一啲嘅要求嘅誒詳細嘅資料啦，包括誒嗰個用地嘅大細啦，誒佢哋誒傾向係邊個地區嗰度興建啦，等等嘅資料。咁民政事務局喺睇到呢一啲資料之後咧，係會檢視咁未。
係誒，唔該，主席。
咁呢個第一個問題啦，第二個問題咧就係誒。
有機會再畀時間你跟翻進呢個項目，因為我其他同事等咗好耐，誒一定會畀時間答入賣地嗰個問題嚇。誒，朱開地議員先唔該。
處瞭解咧，其實大部分嘅少數族裔團體去申請嘅時候咧，都合乎佢哋嘅資格，係可以申請豁免呢一啲嘅租金嘅。
咁政府新一屆政府係會唔會可以話畀我哋聽，新界咧係會有喺政府嘅協助之下，有翻自己第一間嘅清真寺嘅？
團體咁包括一啲誒少數族裔嘅宗教團體啦，係通知佢呢一個信息，咁等佢可以考慮咧喺呢啲清單上面咧，係揾到合適嘅地方咧去進行宗教嘅用途嘅。
咁另外一個渠道咧，就係如果相關嘅申請者已經係心目中有一個誒誒物色咗合適嘅用地嘅話咧，其實咧又可以咧透過咧向地政總署申請，以一啲短期租約嘅方式咧去申請誒批地嘅。咁呢一方面咧，民政事務局咧同樣咧亦都會考。
咁另外就係除咗呢一啲嘅渠道咧，我哋都理解咧，小數族嘅團體咧，誒大部分未必好似一啲商業嘅團體或者一啲大型嘅慈善機構噉樣咧，係有咁大嘅規模或者嘅財政上係咁咁誒能夠可以負擔有零。
sorry，請繼續啦。哦，由零去起一啲嘅宗教場地，咁所以我哋都咧好希望咧係透過一啲其他合適嘅渠道咧係可以幫到一啲少數族裔嘅宗教團體咧係可以揾到一啲地方咧係進行宗教用途嘅。咁呢個包括咧係用一啲善用一啲空置嘅校舍啦。
去做一啲嘅宗教或者文化活動嘅用途。咁好似啱啱今年咧三月咧，地政總署就公佈咗一個清單，就係一啲誒空置校舍咧，係可以畀一啲非政府組織咧去申請誒用嚟做短期嘅用途。噉我哋隨即咧亦都咧係誒發信通知咧一啲主要嘅宗教。
噉，亦都除此之外咧，當然我哋有民政事務總署核下嘅社區會堂同社區中心啦。嗰一啲咧，亦都係一個方便嘅渠道咧，可以畀到誒少數族裔團體咧去舉行一啲宗教或者係文化社區活動嘅。咁嗰啲咧，其實誒我哋係會收一個租金，但係其實咧，我哋同民政。
咁而誒同樣啦，喺康文署核下嘅一啲嘅設施方面咧，亦都係同樣少數族裔團體可以申請用作呢個文化或者康樂嘅用途。咁而租金方面咧，亦都係符合資格咧，係可以有一個優惠，係可以申請嘅。誒或者主席，我先講到呢度先啦，好唔好？有機會我再畀啲。
主席，佢完全未答我嘅問題啊！佢係用咗我嘅時間咧，係回應翻團體嘅一啲。好啊，或者噉樣，誒，我照賠我畀多兩分鐘時間你問。但係佢答翻我嗰兩個案例，上水同埋油麻地。好啊，陳女士有冇回應？好好好啊，誒，就住嗰兩個個案咧，我都有啲資料補充。
畀委員知道嘅咁誒上水嗰個個案先啦。其實喺零六年嘅時候咧，政府係已經批咗呢一笪地噉，所以頭先議員提到嘅話，居民可能有啲反對聲音同埋一啲地價嘅問題咧，其實誒可以咁講，都叫做係解決咗到告一段落，即係已經係批咗呢個土地。
咁點解會中間誒有一段嘅時間喺度咧？其實我哋一路都誒透過地政總署咧，都同相關嘅團體緊密聯繫，因為咧相關嘅團體咧誒要要誒，其實喺零六年批咗嗰笪地之後嘅五年咧，其實係根據個合約咧，佢已經應該要開始認。
運㗎啦噉，但係當中我哋理解，相話團團體內部係有啲問題出現咗啦。咁變咗佢哋開始營運嗰個日期咧，係要褪遲嘅。咁喺呢一方面咧，其實政府已經係誒民政事務局亦都畀咗政策支持咧，係多次已經係誒同意佢去延遲呢一個開始營運嘅日期。咁喺最
最新一次，我哋今年嘅夏天咧，亦都係再一次同相關團體有個會面啦。咁想即係多多瞭解佢究竟最新嘅情況係點樣。噉我哋都咧係會緊密聯係啦，同佢哋即係希望呢個誒計劃咧可以係快啲落實嘅。咁誒，你由萬地嗰度咧，你唔介意或者我轉頭？
誒，我都係想誒探討翻呢個誒伊斯蘭教嗰個宗教用地嘅問題啦。咁基本上，主席大家即係睇翻嗰個資料，就係新界區係冇一個即係正式嘅清真寺嘅，噉就已經主權移交二十年啦。噉我就想問。
即係而家特區政府好似阿林鄭月娥咧，係喺嗰個即係同呢啲伊斯蘭團體嘅見面嘅時候，係有啲嘅啊，即係對佢哋有啲正面嘅回應，就話其實薪價係應該有升增子嘅。我就想問，因為而家上水嗰單case係拱咗畀佢哋啊嘛，即係佢哋其實係求救緊啊嘛，噉。
學校加埋佢哋宗教機構係可以做得到咧，咁呢個第二個。
加埋一啲誒伊斯蘭誒嘅宗教學校噉樣啦，咁咧就誒。
將一塊農地咧，就去誒做一個誒親親子加埋社區中心。
誒問題，噉係因為佢哋冇申請過啊，因為係政府係考慮過之後係冇答應過佢哋一批一個噉嘅地畀佢哋。
噉就誒第三個問題咧，就係喺誒我我係誒新界西嗰度咧，錦上路咧最近就有一個規劃申請嘅，就係誒。
做到啊，冇幫手做得到，所以先至令到嗰啲以俄全俄啊嗰類嘅，即係其實冇基礎嘅反對係會，即係一有呢啲規限申請咧，就bang一聲就幾百個、上千個噉樣出現咯。噉我主要呢三個誒面向，希望畀先生睇下先。
頭先我聽到就係誒就話其實可以主動去申請啦，即係誒啲團體，如果宗教用地方面，我係想具體去講一個情況，就係學校啊，誒主席，譬如話而家新市鎮有好多誒，佢會搞學校㗎嘛，噉我哋見到其實過二十年又係你見到會有基督。
基督教或者天主教嘅團體，佢搞到學校，其實佢係一一物二用㗎嘛。佢會有學校同時間都係嗰個宗教嘅誒機構。咁過去嘅二十年係唔係即係冇任何例子係伊斯蘭教係有同樣嘅一個誒？
其實係按城市規劃條例咧，嗰個誒宗教用途係作為呢個第二欄嘅用途，即係話經過城規會嘅批准咧，係可以做嘅。咁發生咩事咧？就係佢哋就揾咗個建築師，就幫佢就畫咗個圖啦，噉樣噉就誒交畀城規會。
咁當然啦，佢哋其實係欠缺好多部門嘅幫助之下咧，就馬上就激起咗即係數二百計嘅居民就去反對佢呢個規劃申請。咁嗰個反對嘅理由咧，就除咗係交通嗰類之外咧，就有一個比較奇怪就係治安。
理由嘅咁呢個係，我覺得阿主席係覺得非常之痛心嘅。即係如果伊斯蘭教嘅朋友佢搞一個教育嘅中心喺個社區，但係係被視為係一個會帶嚟治安問題咧，噉我覺得民政處喺呢度就有一個角色啦。即係你係咪應該去？
冇話記錄上係咪喎？嗱，點解我問咧？主席，我係質疑佢哋嘅數據可能係。
誒遺漏啦，或者或者低估嘅原因就係最少我自己，我相信其他同事都有跟進啦。
已經顯示曬，其實即係冇乜幫助。當然，問誒正話，秘書長講咗啦，有一啲既有嘅誒。
即係我覺得呢個數字已經説咗説話。另一份文件咧，就係文件可説話就係民政事務局咧呢份文件，我覺得好笑，主席。
佢所講話香港對少數族有種隱性歧視，我覺得睇數字啦，主席睇文件咧，呢個真係顯性到不堪，係咪？包括我哋手上嘅誒。
佢咧新界東都係咧係特別誒多少做住聚居嘅，依個客觀分佈上有數據啦。噉我就覺得嗱，我就你只話提到你話你有八單申請啊嘛，係咪？過去我想問下你有冇一啲其中有冇一單係喺葵涌區嘅麗景附近嘅申請啊？
帶佢哋去傾咧，都傾咗幾次。我印象中，我寫推薦信都寫咗兩次，就係佢密地嘅記錄。嗱，我希望佢咧嚟緊畀埋有關資料我哋。我希望嗰個數嘅準確嘅。如果兩者唔係identical咧，我都係需要跟進嘅。即係我唔係話追究佢有冇人做樓，而係即係。
幫手去話畀嗰啲社區人士聽，其實清真寺即係宗教同埋呢一類嘅學校，係幫啲小朋友，即係佢哋小組做嘅小朋友係學誒佢哋做好人嘅，而唔係帶嚟治安問題嘅。即係呢一個功夫，我覺得民政處係冇。
好啊，主席或者誒就住朱議員誒最後嗰點，或者我可唔可以會後同朱議員瞭解多少少嗰個特別嘅個案，等我哋可以方便我哋直接跟進一下呢個誒第一點就係話喺新界嗰度興建清真寺噉，同我頭先講嗰個咧，其實誒就係相關嘅團體，若果係誒。
同我哋申請用地嘅話咧，我哋係可以咧同規劃處聯繫咧，係幫佢去誒物色適合嘅土地嘅。咁而事實上咧，好坦白噉樣講咧，喺而家港島區同埋九龍區咧，要揾到一笪合適用嘅土地，而又可以攞嚟做永久用途咧。
其實係困難嘅，反而可能喺新界咧，仲會比較冇咁困難，都未定噉。但係當然要睇翻相關團體嘅嘅要求啦。土地有冇現成申請緊？會唔會幾時候第一間咧個問題？誒，其實我哋喺手上咧，我哋咧或者同委員都分享一下。我哋過去三年咧，其實有八宗呢一啲噉樣嘅。
嘅地批地嘅申請嘅噉，亦都唔少咧，係誒伊斯蘭教組織嘅。咁其中有一個誒，請繼續先係嗰個個案咧，本身咧都係話喺九龍嗰度係想誒新界揾地嘅。咁但係就係因為喺九龍嗰度咧揾唔到啦。噉我哋後屘咧係喺誒新。
新界嘅地區咧，係而家係會有機會咧揾到一笪合適嘅土地嘅，咁所以嗰個都會係一個誒可以睇到嘅一個例子。咁誒另外一點咧，就係學校加宗教設施嗰度咧，我自己本身唔係好誒，我哋留意唔到呢一個case，或者我哋。
翻去都同教育局嗰邊聯係一下，睇下知多少少呢個會唔會容易啲嘅？有學校加宗教或者譬如清真寺噉樣。因為你雲店，你都係要搞學校㗎嘛。嗯。而家得我，照我理解，只得一個喺大坑，即係喺喺雲景道嗰度有一間，噉就係學校學校係伊斯蘭學校嚟嘅。係。
係，噉就冇其他例子啦。好似嗯，我哋翻去或者你寫收集嘅例子嚇，有機會嘅話書面回應我哋好嘛？好啊，好啊。誒，跟住我哋又請尹兆堅議員計。多謝主席。剛才啊，有議員同事啊，張超雄提到咧，就係話即係好痛心啦。我覺得誒，即係有種叫歧視，我覺得已經唔係我哋個。
誒立法秘書處幫手做嘅資料統計啦，即係你見到伊斯蘭教，我哋表三嗰度有伊斯蘭教，以至係其他宗教，包括誒誒石黑教、印度教、猶太教等等，有嘅一啲嘅宗教場地少到幾不堪咧。主席你睇睇，咁有好多區域係零添嘅。
濫竽充數，點解咧？你睇後邊嗰兩版其實唔係好關事，我哋講緊場地，後邊咧就都揾啲嘢執下來講啦，都有啲支援服務嘅，有翻譯嘅，我都搞個文化節啦噉樣，主席，即係即係應付下你老人家，應付下我哋噉，叫頂住檔嘅嘢，覺得好離譜呢份文件。你睇下前邊所講嗰啲，我覺得就。
誒主席，誒就住呢個預留土地嗰度咧，我哋而家現行嘅做法咧，就係。
主動一啲嘅方法去處理，包括可能有啲嘢出咗你嘅範圍，但我覺得民政事務局要協調嘅就係，例如喺發誒喺發展新發展區嘅時候。
呢一度咧係誒都可以講係有一個誒預留咗嘅作用喺度嘅，咁嗰八隻case咧，我哋係可以之後誒書面補翻嗰個資料畀各位嘅。好唔該，畀少少，跟住咧請阿麥美娟議，唔該。
邊個組織啊？等我哋可以知道跟進，可以做得到嘛？嗰樣可以啊，可以做得到。咁請你回答第二個問題，關於政策上，特別啲新區嘅發展嘅時候，會唔會有啲預留地方畀有關嘅誒一啲消逐藥嘅機構或者宗教團體申請呢樣嘢？你回應下唔該。好啊。
好啊！咁倒翻轉頭，即係呢一個佢哋嘅宗教，我哋唔可以去揾啲地方去幫下佢哋手咧。咁所以，我第一希望你哋，如果你做呢個公民事務嘅話，你就要幫下手喺呢個公民教育開始做起。咁第二就係喺場地嗰度，誒，我諗你需要需要協助我哋，唔單止誒。
大路嘅所謂民政事務局嘅職能咁嗰啲唔使明㗎，你係要做嘅。而家我哋質疑就係你哋係咪做得唔夠，或者做得唔好咁？我咪我哋未，我唔敢即刻就斷定你哋係先啦。但係一定做得唔足先啦。即係如果唔係，我相信我哋今日唔使咁多少做嘢團體朋友嚟到去申訴。而咧，我想話畀你聽，新界西區。
誒喺部門或者喺局方，佢理解嘅所謂嗰啲申請或者嗰啲訴求，幾時係一個正式嘅official嘅申請，定係哦你噏下嘅啫噉樣嗱？我唔知係咪去到咁差嘅情況啊，因為咧誒，我都有少唔耐煩，因為試過咧帶佢哋啲團體去見部門咧好多次嘅，包括誒見房屋處又好。
好，幾個部門都好。每次其實去到最尾咧，都有多少同民政事務局有關聯啦。就係哦，噉我咪諮詢下咯。你去到房屋處有個空間，你咪抽咯。你抽得贏啲誒社會服務機構嘅抽中咗咪好嘢，抽中咗就問㗎。有地區會會反對咪冇咯嗱。我就覺得呢個係咪就係所謂民政事務局或者民政事務處嘅角色咁簡單？
喺誒説服團體意志協助方面，所以我具體有幾問題。第一，我想問翻嗰條數啊，即係黨乜具體啲交畀我哋話畀我哋聽，有邊八個團體過去申請過嘅地點。我我相信我哋同事好有興趣對一對，我哋自己有跟過嗰啲會唔會都喺入邊。第二，我想問下局方會唔會喺政策上有啲誒主？
誒一啲區域嘅設施，包括呢啲綜合服務大樓等等，會唔會預留設施喺公共屋邨？會唔會預留一啲設施嘅空間，係畀呢啲團體去申請？咁咧就勉強咧，即係你搬入去嘅時候，譬如公屋居民又好，咩區居民都好，入到你知道有相關設施，無論老人中心又好，誒誒青少年中心。
好遠射又好，你唔會話我我入到嚟先發覺，跟住你講一大堆理由話交通又剩嗰啲嘢啦，你入邊知㗎嘛？噉我覺得會唔會喺大政策上有所配合？如果唔係呢個問題，我相信主席係重複又重複係解決唔到嘅。好啊，李主張或者你下次有機會嘅時候，具體嘅係等緊嘅申請咧，嗰啲譬如話地方啊或者。
政府喺規劃一個地區嘅土地用途嘅時候咧，會預留一啲土地作為誒政府機構或社區用地嘅。咁呢一啲即係GIC用地咧，其實係可以用嚟做宗教嘅設施嘅。咁當然睇下有冇其他嘅誒誒迫切、更加迫切嘅土地嘅需求啦。咁所以喺呢～
主席，我哋今日咧，其實講嗰啲場地嘅問題咧，其實我唔係好明。我哋即係淨係揾到誒民政事務局嘅同事嚟咧，究竟可以有即係幾大嘅幫到我哋啦嚇。當然，我哋明可能喺一啲誒寺啊廟啊，咁可能就需要你哋一啲嘅支持啦。咁但係其實有啲好實際嘅，譬如。
譬如我哋誒啲居民，好似嗯，其實好多都好多同事都講咗誒。我哋喺新界西其實特別多嗯少數族裔嘅居民嘅咁有啲喺公共屋邨裏邊，其實誒其實好多都係唔會想誒要行好遠㗎啦，咁都係想喺自己條村度，可能有啲地方啊噉樣，但係房。
處係唔會去去理嘅，即係你同佢房屋處講咧，噉佢係唔會理你嘅。噉就叫你去book社區會堂咯，你唔係去爭社區會堂咯。咁但係其實我諗，我哋即係希望咧，政府部門嘅同事咧明白點解呢啲團體咁希望能夠有一個地方啫，因為佢哋嗰個誒文化。
兩個問題，秘書長唔該。好啊。
誒誒，一視同仁嘅嘅做法喺度啦，噉樣。
可以跨部門去揾到適合嘅場地用咧噉。
即係用擺明腳馬用用宗教行先，但係實際上做好多福利啊、教育啊、好多其他跟手嘢。
專組係負責協助頭先講緊嘅咁多個團體，佢哋去揾場地嘅時候遇到咁多個問題，有冇專人可以幫佢哋嘅咧？其實而家。
如果你冇嘅唔緊要，如果你冇嘅，你會唔會日後考慮有啲噉嘅專人可以幫助呢啲咁多個團體去解決佢哋面對佢哋揾場地面對嘅困難咧？
阿美娟，陳小姐，我我想問一個問題啫。其實咧，你哋個局咧，而家有冇一啲專人或者專責小組係做緊幫少數族裔嘅誒市民，佢哋揾呢啲場地㗎？
咧頭先都好多團體都講咗，佢哋係會有有一啲自己一齊誒誒做誒宗教嘅儀式啦，又或者係一齊學習嘅儀式啦，學佢哋嘅語文，學佢哋嘅經文等等。咁呢啲係所以佢哋需要一啲固定嘅地方，就唔係好似咧火處話，即係你去book我哋條村個社區會堂堂。
爭咧，因為你爭唔到咁點咧？噉佢哋需要一個固定嘅時間，一啲固定嘅嘅嘅嘅日子嘅。咁其實亦都正如由即係將我哋都講啦。其實我哋能夠有呢啲誒機會，畀佢哋特別係佢哋嘅年輕一代，佢哋去教翻佢哋學翻佢哋自己嘅嘅語文，學翻佢哋嘅宗教，學翻佢哋歷史。
其實係教好嘅人嘅喎，唔係好似有啲人以為話，即係會會擺擺班人喺度，好似唔知發生啲咩事啊噉樣。所以我覺得其實即係第一，即係誒，我唔知道阿阿秘書長你個位就係公文事務啦。咁呢個公文事務第一係咪可以幫下我哋手，令到喺社會裏邊大家都明白，即係點解我哋需要有啲噉嘅。
場地或者明白大家唔同嘅誒種族，大家嗰個需要，即係我哋即係等於我哋都會想話一。不過我哋係一年一次，即係如果誒誒潮州人佢哋誒嗰個七月十四係嘛嗰個，其實都係嗰類啫嘛。咁咪咁大啲，我哋出去受盛，我哋一人一次，噉我哋就會好盡量去entertain佢哋，幫佢哋受。
誒呢啲誒，你哋自己揾嘅地方啦嚇。咁但係頭先我講嘅屋村裏邊啦，又或者康文處，康文處而家其實大家好多場地要做體育運動㗎嘛，活動㗎嘛。佢唔係日隨便可以借到喺區裏邊嘅其他場地去做㗎嘛，因為佢哋佢哋要講話啊。如果係宗教嗰啲就唔關佢事㗎啦噉。噉你點樣可以有啲協助到佢哋？
好啊，多謝主席。誒，噉我當然會誒，除咗我負責宗教聯繫事務之外，我都會帶個信息翻去嘅。即係我都非常之同意咧，我哋係要即係教育個市民，即係唔同宗教嘅特色啊，或者要互相尊重呢一樣嘢。咁另外場地方面咧，我理解咧，或者。
少少資料補充畀委員知道，我嚟之前都有向房屋署去了解過佢哋公屋裏面嗰啲設施個租用嗰個情況。噉佢目前咧嗰個租用咧嗰個誒使用嗰個誒活動個場地咧有個要求咧，就係佢要係一個直接嘅福利用途。噉佢哋講緊嘅福利用
可可能係一啲誒青少年中心啊，或者護護理安老院啊等等。咁宗教活動咧就未必可以跌入佢嗰個用途個範圍。咁但係當然，我哋理解呢一個都會係誒少數族裔團體誒其中一個比較可能係希望使用嘅場地。噉我哋呢一個都會帶翻翻。
去誒同房屋署去誒誒分享呢一個嘅意見嘅。咁另外就係話康文署等等嘅場地係咪可以用嚟做宗教啊嗰啲用途咧？咁其實誒議員都講得好啱，就係康文署嘅場地都會係誒畀人用嚟做體育啊文化嘅活動嘅用途啦。咁但係
宗教誒活動嘅用途咧，亦都係可以申請嘅。咁但係當然，大家都係一視同仁，先到先得嘅申請方式啦。咁誒，所以呢一度咧，誒康文署嘅嘅核下嘅設施咧，亦都係可以使用。不過就可能要係同其他嘅活動嘅服務咧有一個誒公平嘅。
誒主席，主席誒，我哋民政事務總署核下咧，有一啲支援服務中心，咁亦都係統籌咧，係幫一啲少數族裔人士咧，係提供一啲協助，或者申請公共服務嘅時候係會提供一啲協助。唔係主席，其實我個問題好清楚、好簡單嘅啫，就係你哋嘅局下底有冇專人或者？
係關於。
其實有冇做緊嘅你哋？
設施就冇因此而多到，而呢個情況唔係發生喺一年，係發生喺十年。
誒，除咗剛剛才講話香誒香港九龍有啊，新新界冇之外咧，同一時間咧。
誒運動嘅，即係話誒之前啊，張開特議員咧喺大個委員會咧都問過呢個問題，就係板球。
除咗最話剛才講嗰啲反對之外啊，地價保地價嗰啲離譜之外咧，其實反對嘅理由咧，真係好令到我哋覺得好好醜怪嘅。
板球咧喺即係巴基斯坦嚟講係好流行，好多後生仔都玩嘅。咁咧就好似香港後生仔打籃球一樣，打踢足球一樣啊咁普遍。
即係誒反對嘅理由，包括係即係有啲就誒都係老老生常談啊，人流誒誒品流複雜啊，交通會會導致有交通塞擠塞啊，噪音擾民啊。
即係誒要進行公眾教育咧，即係我哋真係仲有漫漫長路，有好多嘢要做嚇。一個第一樣，第二樣咧就係關於即係即係阿張愛迪議員都不斷問喺新界嘅即係誒青津子嘅問題。
仲係講緊呢啲理由咧，就真係令到我哋好醜怪。即係我覺得誒誒呢部分，你哋係講緊公民事務咧，呢啲真係都同公民教育有關。即係我我我我希望你明白呢啲，我哋。
有冇專責小組嘅？誒，主席，好似我頭先噉樣提係誒民政總署核下嘅小數族裔支援中心裏面嘅職員咧，係好樂意去協助呢啲小數族裔團體申請公屋嘅。即冇啦，即冇啦嚇。但因為職永久嗰啲有咁困難，臨時嗰啲咧都唔夠人爭，而且人哋好多時係。
誒到轉，你哋又當咗佢哋係宗教，所以你就唔係好理佢哋，因為佢哋唔係福利為主。咁以後佢哋咪應該合合擺福利行先，就會快啲著數啲咧。亦都唔一定唔應該噉樣做法，所以我都覺得大家問啲問題都係個方向都係好緊要，就係話似乎冇咩政策冇咩資源係特別幫一啲少數族裔，特別啲唔同嘅宗教睇。
翻個表咧，必須幫你做個表咧。的而且確係好多誒，表面上正如剛才尹志基員所講咧，就係嗰個個fit個facts fit for itself，即係其實係好好清楚，明顯係唔夠嘅。噉我希望呢邊我插嘴少少咧，希望你即係翻去好好地去睇睇點情況噉。誒，我唔好咗，跟住有兩位同事等緊。誒，邵家津議員唔該，唔該。
主席，誒，如果真係按下誒首席助理秘書長陳小姐所講咧咁順利啊嚇，琴日咁周長嘅話咧，其實今日個公聽會唔使搞啦，係咪？佢廿幾個團體上嚟就係話畀你聽，即係而家個有一機制，就如果係有嘅話，其實真係唔係好work啦。咁咧就誒，今日當然同我哋講緊係。
係文明嘅衝突啦，嚇！即係如果嚴格嚟講，咁呢個呢個現象咧，都唔係淨係得香港有。不過咧，我就係聽完之後咧，我發覺香港呢一種嘅衝突咧，就水平咧，真係太令人失望嚇。誒，即係講緊就張崇議員講起上水清真寺嗰個發展計劃咧啊。
誒呢啲都明白㗎，但係咧有啲咧竟然係係擔心咧嗰啲派藝派啊，誒嗰啲教派衝突啊，會會引致咧激烈行動啊，殃及居民嘅生命財產啊，或者係誒破壞中國人嘅風水啊噉樣。喂，呢啲理由咧而家講緊，而家呢啲又仲係發生緊，仲。
喺香誒嗰啲小户族裔嘅朋友咧，巴基斯坦啊，同埋印尼嘅誒印尼嘅朋友咧，好多時候係住咗喺新界超過一半嘅巴基斯坦人同埋印尼人咧，喺二零一一六年嘅統計裏邊咧住喺新界，而佢哋喺新界嘅總人數咧，喺過往嘅十年咧增加咗八十七個percent，即係話人就多咗，但係宗教。
即係所以點解大家咁阿華設始講緊喺新界區點解可以點解後屘盡快有咧噉樣？當然你係講緊都有一啲申請進行緊啦，有啲project可能有啲醖釀緊啦噉樣。但係我哋希望真係快啲有啦，唔係話喂十年啊，因為問題已經發生喺十年，仲要等幾多年咧噉樣？另一個具體問題。
咁咧就以前咧有啲人咧就話誒板球場不足啦噉樣，但係我咧就見到其實好多E.M.嘅細路仔咧喺公園嗰度玩，喺籃球場嗰度玩，仲係即係一有一有地方唔畀人講嘅話，佢就喺度玩。噉我覺得咧，有時咧，除咗係場地夠唔夠之外咧，就係資訊嘅問題。
誒叫做誒。
調翻轉嚟講，你話乜教佢點樣book咧？誒，有關嘅開放時間嗰啲嘢咧，唔該主席。
整個一個新嘅場地，一個臨時嘅quicket ground，咁咧呢個場地咧預計喺二零一八年初咧就會啟用嘅啦。
足級啊！板球協會咧，Hong Kong Cricket Association咧，就有合作搞啲活動，同埋係揾一啲誒呢啲適合板球活動嘅場地嘅。噉佢哋喺呢個嘅誒醉酒灣嗰度咧，就誒啱啱應該就係。
佢語言上有啲障礙啊，或者唔知道個渠道應該係喺邊個部門去申請啊？我哋嗰啲都會提供一啲嘅資訊嘅，或者我睇下康文署同事會唔會再有啲？好啊，葉生係咪？請我補充啊！多謝主席。
場啦，同埋係有三個嘅誒誒人造草場咧，係可以適合做呢個板球嘅活動嘅。咁即係隔埋嗰度有係有十個場地啦。咁呢啲場地咧都係可以即係喺誒公開畀公眾租用嘅。咁另外咧就係誒康文署亦都有同呢個誒香港嘅誒。
就係，即係根本佢哋又唔知道邊度有板球場，根本咧更加唔知道咧板球場嘅開放時間，更加唔知道咧點樣book板球場。即係政府喺呢方面咧，點樣可以令到嗰啲誒青少年朋友係知道呢啲呢啲資訊，令到佢真係唔好講，唔好講佢肯唔肯book啊！
有幾多個板球場？主席，C C C C之外，我唔知啊。係誒，主席或者我誒可能詳細情形，我請康文處同事去補充。但係我講少少先啦。誒，而家其實康文處係係有兩個板球場嘅，一個喺九龍城天光道遊樂場，另外一個喺黃大仙蒲江村道公。
遠噉，我哋都知道咧。其實誒，大家市民對於唔同康體活動場所嘅需求好殷切啦。咁所以康文署咧，而家都計劃緊起多一啲多用途嘅球場，去滿足唔同嘅運動嘅需要。咁誒，另外點樣去誒book呢？
啲場地啊，各樣其實咧就係點樣去使用呢啲公共服務嗰個渠道嗰個使用嗰個情況。咁特別針對少數族裔人士咧，誒，好似我頭先所講，我哋民政總署下下嘅支援中心咧嘅職員咧，亦都係隨時咧歡迎即係去協助一啲誒少數族裔團體或者。
誒喺康文署嘅場地裏邊咧，就誒除咗剛才提過有兩個專用嘅誒板球場啦，即係喺呢個誒浦天光道嘅，同埋呢個係誒黃大仙嘅浦江村啦。咁另外其實我哋仲有係誒揾到咧，有其實有七個嘅場地，包括咗係誒有七個嘅硬地嘅足球。
就係你嗰啲噉嘅足球場啊、草地場，你唔係隨便可以租嚟做木球用途㗎嘛？係嘛？誒，佢係可以適合嗰個用途嘅，即係都可以冇限制。佢哋可以改係咧，因為我哋通常啲場地都係呢啲場地係一啲比較上叫誒multi-purpose嘅場地。但係，主席呢啲一定要團體申請嘅，呢啲啊，你要講清楚，個人係申請唔到嘅呢啲係咪啊？
甚至乎。
細啊，同埋佢哋希望都喺油麻地同埋佐敦嘅地區嗰度，可以揾翻一個用地。
我哋翻去同教育局一齊研究一下。係咯，好啊，好啊。周定賢，你有冇其他跟進？O K，好得。誒，有少時間咧，剩翻剛才啊，張超如問起，我應承咗畀佢答翻嘅，關於嗰個油麻地個場嘅問題。主席，你有冇補充翻呢樣嘢？好啊，好啊，多謝主席。
誒誒，葉生係要團體先可以申請。誒，應該係要團體申請嘅嚇。咁因為誒，如果呢個quick kick嘅運動都係誒，或者我哋會同呢個即係誒quick quick kick association嗰邊咧都會有啲配合。噉你翻去睇睇關注多少少呢個問題，因為實上都係一個大家都知道，特別喺我嘅住過都知道咧，誒板球隊好多誒，特別係少數族人嚟講係。
個好大嘅spot嚟嘅嚇。OK，誒對唔住啊，周浩鼎議員等咗耐啦。周浩鼎議員係係唔該，主席係誒噉就我有個意見咧，就想提出，即係因為而家今日個會嘅，大家所有啲代表都表達咗咧，就係即係長期嘅又睇嚟好似望唔到噉啊，短期咧我。
我頭先甚至乎聽到咧，有啲話短期嘅租約都去到三廿九萬，係嘛？即係啲啲好貴嘅一個租金噉。我我就想提一個意見咧，就係其實今日都有與會者，我見到有啲書面嘅意見寫得幾好嘅，裡面都有提咧，就係話喂，其實如果你話畀佢哋一啲嘅少數族裔進行佢哋，無論係宗教。
或者佢哋嗰個誒，佢哋自己嘅文化活動咧，其實學校就係咪一個好好嘅地方可以做到咧？嗱，如果你比如話畀到提供到學校畀佢哋，其實佢哋同時間就用埋嗰個學校嚟做埋一啲定期嘅活動，噉你其實一石二鳥喎，即係會唔會呢個係一個你哋可以諗下嘅方向咧？
如果你話誒遠水不能救近火啦，即係人哋等咗咁耐，噉我不如咁有個建議咧，就係而家其實喺新界西咧，即係無論你話元朗啊、屯門呢啲，比較多小數聚，不如你集中啲，會唔會揾同事咧去統籌一下新界西嘅學校？新界西嘅學校統籌咗咧，睇下做啲協調。
會唔會喺呢啲學校能夠借出啲定期嘅場地畀佢哋去做佢哋要做嗰啲文化、宗教或者福利嘅活動？噉你就起碼可以比較容易咁先解決到佢而家一路等緊嗰個誒場地嘅使用。當然長遠你哋要做嘅，即係你長遠，比如話誒，佢哋需要一啲長遠嘅誒。
誒誒場地去做嗰個，亦都要需要解決。但係短期咧，會唔會你可以做呢啲統籌嘅功夫，協作到一啲新界西嘅學校借畀佢哋，等佢哋可以即刻就用到咧？噉啊，唔使成日都一路人哋個個都話等啊，等好耐，搞啊，搞好耐，一路都都借你哋康文處啲場，又話揾唔到嘅，即係可。
我我我建建議可唔可以咁考慮呢個第一點？另外咧，第二點咧就係講頭先講板球，大家都傾過噉啊。其實老實講咧，即係如果你話誒有嗰個場地，我哋都成日講咧，以後日後政府做嗰啲草地咧，我都希望建議係多用途嘅啊，即係唔止板球啦，欖球又用得足球。
又可以用到練習。你你話係咪要嚟做比賽咧？我知道個規格未必一樣，但係起碼做練習可以畀到人哋嘅練習。同埋嗰個團體租用嗰度咧，或者你到去翻去可以檢視下啦。咁其實好老實講，玩板球咧，我記得以前細個，因為我喺英國以前寄宿學校咧，我見到啲鬼好中意咧，就係攞個網球。
都攞嚟掟，即係照樣，即係佢未必真係下下都要用到嗰個真係嗰個佢好硬嗰個quick嘅個波嘅，佢有時用個網球自己喺個橫街窄巷噉，佢已經可以玩啦。不過即係無論如何點都好咧，我覺得都要正視人哋係真係有呢一個嘅需求。噉我覺得你話喺用團體去book或者即係瞭解下點解人哋。
可能咁耐以嚟未必有辦法可以用到嗰個練習嘅場地。我希望你翻去檢視一下呢個情況，好嘛？個意見另外一個可以計選舉用途計拍校巴之外，學校都可以馬上有啲嚇更更改用途啊。噉啊，可以諗諗咧，呢個係個方法，特別新界西誒特別比較嚴重嘅地區啊，秘書長。嗯，主席我。
由一月份開始到到去到七月份都已經有㗎啦，咁但係誒，似乎我哋喺三月份咧有個關於。
可以誒，將我哋剛才三位同事提出嘅就業問題咧，係加落去裏邊嗰度。咁大家有冇咩意見？因為如果冇咧，我就將畀住安排呢方面咁做法。有冇咩具體意見？
誒揾揾到揾一大餐，揾揾可能揾半年之後話佢聽，啊冇啊唔好意思，跟住誒就請佢調整，調佢傾完調整完又再又而家又再揾過，可能又揾半年。
即係呢啲係咩世紀嘅溝通嚟嘅咧？即係我你如果係積極去幫一個少數族裔或者一個宗教團體去揾地咧，你唔係噉樣啊嘛！即係呢種係完全係迴避嘅態度，唔係積極嘅態度。
喺誒油麻地嗰一個誒喺海皇道係海皇道嘅誒政府土地咧誒，或者我補充少少資料畀各位委員知悉誒。喺其實喺二零一二年嘅時候咧，我哋已經係以短期租約嘅形式咧，係租咗畀誒合眾福利社去營運。而家頭先。
誒各位團體所提誒團體所提及到嘅喺油麻地嘅清真寺嘅咁喺當時嗰個租約咧，就喺二零一三年二月嘅時候就生效咗。咁最初嘅租期咧係去到二零一四年嘅十二月三十一號。咁喺簽誒個租約嘅時候咧，已經講明咧，因為嗰一笪嘅土地咧係。
屬於中九龍幹線嘅工程嘅範圍之內，咁於是乎咧，嗰一個租約咧係不設續約嘅條款嘅。咁但係咧，因為及後咧，中九龍幹線工程都有一啲嘅調整啦，嗰個施工嘅時間表，咁所以誒喺民政事務局嘅政策支持同埋路政處嘅同意之下咧，嗰
個租約嘅屆滿日期咧，先後都延長咗三次，咁最後一次咧就係今年嘅年底十二月三十一號。噉我哋喺呢個期間咧，亦都多次同地政總署都同合眾福利社咧係緊密聯繫，因為知道嗰個租約期都就嚟滿咧，亦都好希望佢哋可以即係繼續佢哋嘅清真。
只提供嘅宗教誒服務係會繼續可以做得到啦。咁所以有少少背景咧，就係我哋其實舊年咧誒夏天嘅時候已經開始，合眾福利社咧都同我哋咧係提過話想有一個覓地嘅要求。咁亦都向我哋咧誒提供咗一啲嘅資料，包括嗰個誒土地嗰個大。
咁隨即咧，我哋亦都聯係咗規劃處，噉就去根據申請人嘅要求咧，去嘗試去物色適合嘅用地。咁但係好可惜咧，我哋就未能夠咧喺誒按申請人嘅要求，即係話喺翻油麻地同埋佐敦裏面去揾到一個申請人要求大細嘅。
用地去畀佢哋，噉我哋亦都誒隨即將個結果咧。今年年中咧，亦都係將呢一個噉樣嘅別地嘅結果咧通知合眾福利社啦。咁亦都建議佢哋睇下可唔可以稍為修整一下佢哋嘅要求，因為要揾到咁上下大嘅土地，亦都喺油麻地同埋佐敦咁擠迫嘅地區咧，係。
有一啲嘅困難嘅咁誒，啱啱我哋喺誒上個月尾，亦都收到合眾福利寫翻翻嚟，有啲有一啲嘅誒少少嘅調整啦。噉我哋亦都將佢哋嘅誒調整咗嘅要求咧，亦都交咗畀規劃處去再睇㗎啦。咁誒，希望可以誒盡快去揾得到呢一個地方咯。咁亦都短期嘅。
措施合眾福利社都提出，即係可唔可以短期有一啲控制校舍可以用住先啊？咁呢啲我哋亦都會同土地啊地政總處去探討嘅。咁呢個係我補充嘅資料，主席。啊，張忠義，你有冇咩跟進啊？呢個問題你發起先嘅嚇，有啊，少時間跟進。即係當然，我誒我亦都希望一間主席畀翻少少時間誒佢哋兩。
兩個相關嘅社團回應一下啦。不過，我聽誒呢位官員講咧，即係啊，首席助理秘書長講咧，就佢嗰個溝通模式咧，好落後啊。即係誒，據據據誒，即係合眾福利社嗰個要求，佢誒誒。
啊！我想問問清楚佢啦，或者咁咧，因為時間關係咧。如果個別個案咧，我哋會有適當嘅跟進佢，或者有翻嘅同事們咧，就有關嘅團體咧，可以再同啊當局咧，可能更加多細節多個事實嘅話，可能更加有效，因為我哋基本上討論政策會比較方便啲，同埋我哋時間上咧都可能咧係唔用我哋好詳細就個案咧。
一個嗰個是是非非作咗一個辯論噉，恐恐怕我哋我哋更加有學跟進方法。不過，我想秘書長誒秘書秘書長咧，就都幾個問題需要跟進下，包括剛才講嗰八個申請咧個細節，等我哋可以知道下每一個區我哋跟緊嘅有冇乜嘢進展啊。第二，好似我哋，例如我哋，譬如好似話一啲嘅誒誒誒。
情況。
嗯。
阿尹兆堅，原嚟舉手。阿主席，我回應你嗰個建議嘅，我就。
噉佢福利嗰邊咧就係唔整討論。唔好意思啊，主席，我我哋雲都仲有第一，仲有一次咧，喺七月份，我哋暫時仲有空檔嘅。如果我哋真係做唔切嘅話咧，我哋喺嗰度可以掌握。唔該，主席，好嘛。因為其他同事冇其他意見嘅話咧，我哋今日嘅誒時間到此為止，好嘛。Okay，thanks very much to all of you for attending. Thank you. Thank you.
誒天橋設施啊，lift塔，我哋都知道啊，做緊未做緊未啦。咁希望你都知道下咁喺嗰八個申請裏邊點做法咧。亂扯。第二咧就係關於個學校用途方面，你話會翻去跟進下咧。第三個問主關於嗰個譬如申請足足場方面，能夠可以做多少少幫到少少族裔，特別係非團體嘅或者有咩可以幫到佢哋手。阿韋兆堅，你有啲舉手報。多謝主席。
誒佢因為佢就係答過我哋咧，就係講用地咧。噉佢純粹答咗一個土地使用嘅政策啫。我希望即係引申你嘅講法，其實我哋講緊就係一個有冇協助少數族裔嘅由民政事務局帶頭嘅一個誒支援政策，協助佢哋喺香港無論宗教以至係其他文化活動嘅申請場地以至其他支援。
我諗跨黨派嘅同事都好清晰嘅立場，就係覺得完全唔足夠嘅。睇翻我哋畀出畀我哋嘅文件裏邊嘅數字咧，似乎好明顯地係有於一對於一啲少數族裔嘅團體宗教方面嘅活動咧，係好大嘅困難。咁呢個我相信當局係係責無旁貸，需要係注視下，因為我哋可能傳統上我哋其他誒天主教、基督教、佛教。
誒道教都好似比較相對嚟講係冇咁大嘅問題，但係少數少數造業嘅問題咧係非常之大，尤其是佢哋而家人口咁多嘅話咧，我諗呢個係唔可以再等好嘛。希望你可以翻去交交代下情況。噉啊，時間上咧，我哋誒祝完結咗第一個個議題㗎啦，多謝曬咁多位參與，thanks very much for attending啊。我哋主要係講翻留翻少少時間。
講講我哋議題，因為我收到有三位同事，包括係有尹兆堅議員啦、毛萬靜議員，同埋最後嘅邵家遵議員都有提出話，希望我哋將嗰個少數族裔嘅就業問題同埋青年就業問題咧，誒或者政策咧係可以係作討論嘅。咁睇翻我哋秘書處幫你安排咗咧，我哋實際上都已經有啲提有啲嘅議題咧係誒由。
誒家暴嘅係咪？係家庭暴力嘅問題咧，喺我哋福利小組方面都會有具體討論嘅。咁睇下我哋會唔會係喺嗰個時候一齊會集中喺嗰個機會講埋啦。如果我哋可以將小組重要問題加埋落去嗰個主流嘅家暴問題一齊講啊，定還是我哋點咧？如果係嘅話咧，我哋三月份嗰個slot個時間咧。
係誒，我睇到雖然未舉手，不過問徐家俊議員好似有表態想講嘢先嚇。我畀畀徐家俊議員。我哋主席誒，作為福利事務委員會嘅主席咧，我想補充一下咧，三月份咧，我哋係會檢視下香港嗰個誒家家暴嘅政策同埋措施。咁但係咧就誒，如果我哋誒特別，我我但係咧我講。
往咧都係比較忽略咗咧，係喺E.M.裏邊嘅誒誒家庭暴力嘅問題嘅。咁所以如果部分嘅時間將個焦點擺喺E.M.嗰度，等我哋可以，譬如話一個combine一個一個聯席嘅或者方面做嘅話，我哋可以一齊做噉，可能會更加大聚焦咁睇睇個家暴，包括無論主流嘅誒人口或者係少數族裔嘅人口係點樣。
我就覺得，如如果嗰次係可以有一啲，今日噉樣咧，有一半嘅時間係公聽會咧，噉就會好啲。但係福利事務委員會嗰嗰日咧，就可能已經係有三三個題目咧，可能未必安排到公聽會，畀佢哋可以直接可以分享到。或者我哋同秘書處夾夾互相夾夾咧，如果係適合嘅我哋做，如果唔適合嘅我哋自己做開一個少數組員嘅家務嘅問題好嘛？
誒拼到啊，儘量都拼個同意原則。不過我就諗唔到暴家庭暴力同工作點拼嚟嘅團體有機會好唔同嘅喎。誒誒，唔係我唔係咁意思。我意思係話，我哋將嗰個本來會討論家暴嗰個環節咧，嗰一段時段嗰一期咧係誒轉嚟做咗誒就業方面嘅議題，就將家暴嗰啲轉咗。